Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to
be looking at conjugate acids and bases.
Now, what this is all about is
that when you have acids and
bases reacting together, they
can reach chemical equilibrium.
Which, what that is, is a concept
that we will, that we will
focus in on in other videos.
But the whole idea is that whenever
you have, let's say, weak acids or weak
bases, which are weak electrolytes,
they generally do not fully dissociate
whenever you put them in solution.
So they don't fall apart as easily.
Now with those, the whole idea is that
their reactions are considered reversible.
Meaning that it, the reaction
can go backwards or it can turn
back from products to reactants.
So whenever we have something in
equilibrium, this is when we say
essentially that the products
and the reactant reactants
are reacting at the same rate.
So we have a four that we
have a forward reaction.
And when we also have a backwards
reaction happening at the same time,
which is a little crazy to think about
that it can get even more complicated.
Now whenever we have essentially
products that can possibly turn
back into reactants, right?
So going backwards, uh, we can
actually use a equilibrium constant
to describe it, especially when
we're talking about solutions.
and gases.
So what this constant
is, is called a K value.
And what it does is it takes the
concentration of the products
and then divides it by the react,
concentration of the reactants.
So it's molarity for the products
on top, and then the molarity
of the reactants on the bottom.
And it's ratio.
So what it tells you is that, okay,
if there's more products, Then the
reaction is going to be a big K value.
It's going to go forward.
And if there's more reactants,
it's going to be a small K value,
meaning the reaction is going
to go backwards as a result.
So which way is that reaction going to go?
Now, from there, whenever we're
indicating these different types of
reactions, the first part is the forward
reaction for what you're used to.
is, is that the forward reaction
is always indicated by an arrow
that's going from left to right.
So it's always going from left to right.
Now a reverse arrow is the opposite.
So it's going from right to left.
So if you have it going from right to
left, that's indicating the reverse.
So now if the fact that we have this
equilibrium process and we have both
forward and backwards, so what we're
going to do is we're going to combine
their powers together And we're going to
make an equilibrium arrow as a result.
So you'll see this double arrow
that's going to be placed in a lot of
reactions that have weak electrolytes.
And that's telling you that the
reaction goes forward and back.
It does not mean you got to do
anything else in terms of balancing
or anything in terms of reactions.
All that's telling you is that the
backwards reaction is possible.
It's the same process that you were
using before, but it's giving you
another piece of information that
the reaction has a tendency to mainly
stay as reactants versus, or mainly
stay as products, right, depending
on the conditions of the reaction.
If we were to try to, uh, let's say label
what we refer to as acid and base pairs.
How exactly can we do that?
Well, the first thing is labeling
what is considered an acid.
So here I have the letters HA to represent
our acid, because acids donate protons.
So what's going to happen is this
HA is going to donate its proton to
the water molecule here, which means
that this is considered the base.
So when we have our final products,
We are going to have A minus as
one answer because HA lost its
proton and then we're going to
have H3O plus as the other answer.
Now what this whole thing about
conjugate acids and bases is about
is that the backwards reaction also
has acids and bases in it as well.
There's a pair of them, meaning
that you have an acid base pair
on the left hand side of the
reaction all the way on over here.
And you also have an acid base
pair on the product side, too.
So if we were to look at this,
what can donate a proton between A
and H3O which one has hydrogens to
give, and you're going to see that,
oh, well, H3O can give a hydrogen.
So what that's going to happen is
this one is going to donate its H plus
to the A minus making HA going back.
So as you can see, these, this one is
related to the molecule on the other side.
So what we can do here is we can label
H3O plus as an acid and A minus as a base.
Now because these are on the product side
of the reaction, This is what we refer to
as a conjugate acid and a conjugate base.
So let's move those names down
a little bit and now we're
going to add the word conjugate.
So
now that we've labeled that, what we
can now see is that there are acids
and bases on the left and the right.
Now the thing about this is
when we're looking at this, that
there is a, there are going to
be two pairs of acids and bases.
So not only are there some on the left
and the right, but there's also between
the two sides of the reaction too.
What you are looking for is common,
essentially common anions or
common cations in these equations.
So for example, one of
them is a minus, right?
So that, as you can see, there's
an a on the conjugate base.
There's also an A on the
left hand side in HA.
So these two together are referred to as
a conjugate acid base pair because they
have the same common ion in each equation.
Now when it comes to the other two,
which is the one with water, well
what's the common piece between H2O?
And H3O plus is water is the
common part of both of them, right?
The only difference is one H plus.
So when you're looking for a
conjugate S base pair, you're looking
for the difference of a single
hydrogen between the two pairs.
So is there a hydrogen difference?
So both of the ones I labeled here
in that yellow and that peach color.
These are referred to as
conjugate acid base pairs.
Let's look at some more examples of this.
Hydrogen, so whether it's present or
it's absent, with the difference of a
proton, that means it was transferred.
So whenever we're looking at these pairs,
right, if we look at the one here, which
is the same we showed before, if I look at
HA and A they differ by a single proton.
So this is one conjugate acid base pair.
On the other hand, we have water and H3O
which also differ by a single proton.
This is the second
conjugate acid base pair.
Every single reaction has a pair.
Let's go and look at more.
Given the following reaction,
determine its conjugate acid
base pair in the reaction.
So what we are looking for is things that
have a difference of a single proton.
So and we also want to be able
to label if it's an acid or
base in the reaction as well.
So if we look, what can we see in terms
of the products and the reactants?
We see ammonia is reacting
with water to create NH4 plus.
So the thing that we want to look
at, if I look at, let's say, water,
we can say that it donated an H plus
to ammonia to make ammonium, right?
So we see the difference on the side here.
So when we label these, we can see
water is behaving like an acid.
And then ammonia is behaving like a base.
So it's pairs in this case is that
H2O is paired with hydroxide, right?
They differ by a single hydrogen, right?
OH is missing one proton.
So what does that make it?
Well, there has to be an acid base pair.
So hydroxide is going to
be the conjugate base.
So if you ever see C O N J
as an abbreviation, that's
referring to conjugate.
So what that means now is that if this
is the conjugate base, then the other
molecule must be the conjugate acid,
which therefore will be paired ammonia.
So these are the two.
Now to check our work, we can
look at the reversible side of the
reaction and see does it agree.
So in that case, ammonium
should donate its proton to
hydroxide to make water, right?
And then you can see that that
matches on the left hand side.
So what we always have to do is we have
to identify what the donor and acceptor
are in our steps, then identify the
pairs and all these different reactions.
Let's take a look at
another example of this.
Given the following reaction,
determine its conjugate acid base pair.
So the first thing we gotta do is
identify the donor and acceptor.
And the acceptor of the protons.
So one thing that we can
see is where is our acid?
And we can see that H two PO
four is donating its proton
to NH three in this case.
So now when that happens, what we,
how we can do to label that is that
means that H two PO four is our
acid, and NH three is the base.
Now, on the opposite side of the
reaction, what's being the donor?
Well, what we can see is that H4
plus is donating its proton to HPO4.
So in this case, we have our
conjugate acid and our conjugate base.
So conjugate acid and then conjugate base.
So now we got a pair up, uh, the
different types of, uh, acid base pairs.
Let's erase these arrows.
So, on the left hand side I will
pair my acid with my conjugate base,
and then on the right side I will
pair up my base and my conjugate
acid, and those are our two pairs.
Let's take a look at some other examples.
So let's say I want to predict
one from start to finish.
How would I do this?
So right here we have HCLO
and CH three and H two.
So the first thing we gotta
do is identify the acid.
Acid always generally has, uh, uh,
h in the front of the reaction.
So what this is gonna be doing
is it's gonna be donating it's
hydrogen to the other species.
So when that happens, well what's gonna
be left is we're gonna have CLO minus,
and that's gonna differ by one proton.
And then the other one
is gonna be CH three.
NH3 plus.
So we have our acid base relationship.
So that means on the other side,
right, NH3 is going to donate
its proton the other way, right?
So we can label everything.
So we have our acid, which is HClO4.
We have our base, which is CH3NH2.
And then we have our base
and acid as well on the other
side, which are our conjugates.
So let's add up all those labels.
Now that we labeled them, what we can
now show is our little lines to kind
of represent the different pairs.
So we have our acid partnered with
our base, and then we'll have our base
partnered with its conjugate acid.
And these are the different
pairs in this reaction.
Let's look at another example.
So a very common question that you
will, that you will receive on exams
or homework or even in the finals
is what is the conjugate acid or
base of the following reaction?
Meaning that you have to be able to
identify if it's an acid or base, and
then determine what would it turn into.
So for the first one, I have
hf, which means that this
is a very common weak acid.
So when that dissociates in water,
what it's going to essentially
make H plus and F minus, right?
So F minus would be its conjugate
base in this type of situation.
So what formula.
Differs by a single proton and
we can't become more positive.
We can always become more negative
when we're looking at that,
looking at those conjugate pieces.
So that is an example
of one on this next one.
This one looks a little bit different
and that's because I wrote it
purposely like an organic acid.
This is the acetate ion connected to a
hydrogen, so it's acetic acid, or vinegar.
So, one way that this can be
seen is the following, CH3COOH.
or it can also be shown as
H2C2H3O2.
So there's another way to represent that.
So that way the hydrogen's in the front.
It depends on kind of
what you're looking at.
So the acidic hydrogen is the one
that's all the way on the end over
here, whereas the acidic hydrogen
is written on the left hand side.
So we have the essentially the CHEM3A
version on the bottom and then the
CHEM3B or organic version on top.
So when this breaks down, We're going
to have our acetate ion is going to
be one structure, and then you're
going to have your hydrogen ion.
So what we will have is we
have our acid and then our
conjugate base on the other side.
So that is our pair.
Now the next one, well, it's NO3 minus
and there's no hydrogen to take from it.
So what does that mean?
Well, if it were, let's say to react
with water, for example, it would end
up receiving one of those hydrogens.
So if you want, you can always
kind of see how would it
actually react with the water.
And if we were to do that, well, we
would end up having h and o three
and oh minus as the other product.
So if we were to try to label that,
this would be the base, and then
this would be your conjugate acid.
In this reaction, they differ
by one single hydrogen.
Now, sometimes they can
be a little bit different.
You could go, potentially,
one way or the other.
So HPO42 you can actually go either left
or right, depending on how you look at it.
So with this one, I can either receive
a proton, or I can take one away.
So being that it's negative,
it could accept more protons.
So either we can make PO4 3 which is the
phosphate ion, or I can make H2PO4, uh,
just minus to receive one more proton.
And if you really want to think
about it, this can even go.
another step where it can receive a
extra one to make phosphoric acid.
So it all depends on how many charges does
it have, how many protons are available.
So with this original question, what
we kind of have here, depending on
which direction you go, could label
it as the acid or base, um, and
with all these different pieces.
So this has been the whole idea
of conjugate acids and base pairs.
So let's kind of summarize it real quick.
So the whole idea of it was that
essentially whenever it comes to these
reactions, you're looking for the acid
and base between the left and the right
that differ by the presence of a single
hydrogen or proton inside of the equation.
If you find that proton difference, you
can label the acid on the left hand side.
or the right hand side.
This is something that's, it's
easy to kind of make mistakes.
So try to practice it, write it on an
index card for that definition so that
way you can remember it for later.
All right.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope this video helped.
If it didn't make sense, please let
me know by sending me a message or
sending me an email or commenting
below on the video, whatever you
need to help you pass chemistry.
Please reach out.
Uh, if this is your first time here,
please hit that like and subscribe button,
and thank you so much for supporting
the channel and watching the video.
I hope you all have a wonderful
day, and I'll see you all later.
Bye now!